Guide to the Andrew Lang Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Andrew Lang collection
1881-1912
GEN MSS 1109
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection contains autograph letters, signed, written by Andrew Lang to acquaintances and colleagues, a photograph of Lang, and a small group of autograph manuscripts.
Lang, Andrew, 1844-1912
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, 1946-2005. Acquisition information appears at the folder level.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Andrew Lang (1844-1912)
Scottish author, folklorist, historian, and literary critic.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains autograph letters, signed, written by Andrew Lang to acquaintances and colleagues, a photograph of Lang, and a small group of autograph manuscripts.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Letters, 1881-1912. II. Writings, 1894-1898.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Authors, English -- 20th Century; English literature -- 19th century; English literature -- 20th Century; Photographs -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Lang, Andrew, 1844-1912
- Letters, 1881-1912; Series I; 36
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged in alphabetical order by recipient; unidentified recipients appear at the end.
  - To Mr. Alden; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Custodial History
    Gift of Bernhard Knollenberg, 1946.
  - To Mr. Allhusen; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - To Mr. Allhusen; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of Abel Cary Thomas (Yale 1905).
  - To H. C. Bailey; autograph letters (5), signed, 1901, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1996.
  - To Mr. Bell (3) and to Mrs. Bell, with an ink sketch of a castle on last page, and to "Hill"; autograph letters (5), signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Accompanied by typescripts of "Over the Wall" and "Mr. Carlyle as a Sentimentalist," by Andrew Lang; photograph by J. Farquhar of Aberdeen of Andrew Lang's gravestone; printed leaflet about the Memorial to Andrew Lang at the University of St. Andrews, with printed image of the Lang memorial tablet.
  - To Edmund Gosse; autograph letter, signed, 1912 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2002.
  - To Sir John Hammerton; autograph letter, signed, 1903 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Gift of Kenneth W. Cameron (Yale 1940 PhD), 1957.
  - To Hannay, to Lady MacAlister, to Miss Parker, to Mrs. Purdie, and to "My dear Sir"; autograph letters (5), signed, 1906, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999.
  - To F. B. Jerous; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2000.
  - To B. Knowles; autograph letter, signed, 1895 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Purchased from Henry Bristow on the Library Associates Fund, 1997.
  - To Mr. Knowles; autograph letter, signed, 1908 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Purchased from Pickering and Chatto on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1997.
  - To Richard Le Gallienne; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2004.
  - To Lady Lindsay; concerning Robert Louis Stevenson; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1997.
  - To Justin Huntly McCarthy; autograph letter, signed, 1911 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of Herman Wardwell Liebert (Yale 1933), 1972.
  - To Mr. McLennan; autograph letters (2), signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - To "Dear Marston"; autograph letter, signed, 1896 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - To Matthew; autograph letter, signed, 1882 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Gift of Abel Cary Thomas (Yale 1905); removed from Lang's Helen of Troy (New York, 1882).
  - To Mr. Melrose; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - To L. S. Metcalf; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2003.
  - To Mrs. Moor, to "Dear Madam," and "To Sir" (5); autograph letters (7), signed., 1897-1912 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    General note
    Accompanied by a typed letter, signed (1920), from Alfred P. Clarke to Mrs. Tilney with an Andrew Lang autograph attached.
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1998.
  - To Mr. Natt; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Gift of Mrs. Charles Kerner, 1957.
  - To Albert Bigelow Paine; autograph letters (6), signed, 1911, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - To Mr. Rideing; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - To Mr. Rideing; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - To Alice Shields; autograph letters (3), signed, 1897-1902 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - To Mrs. Stedman; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
  - To Mr. Steel; autograph letters (2), signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2005.
  - To W. Irving Way; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - To unidentified recipients
    - To "Dear Sir"; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel (Yale 1935), 1951.
    - To "Dear Sir"; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Gift of Leslie Hotson, 1984.
    - To "Gentlemen" (unidentified publisher) concerning Sir Walter Scott; autograph letters (2), signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - To "Dear Sir"; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - To "My dear Sir"; autograph letter, signed, accompanied by a photograph of Andrew Lang, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - To "Dear Sir"; autograph letters (2), signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - To "Gentlemen" (unidentified publisher or literary agent); autograph letter, signed, 1899? Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - To "Dear Sir"; autograph letters (2), signed, circa 1881, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Writings, 1894-1898; Series II; 9
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Ballade of Yule"; autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1997.
  - "El Desdichado"; autograph manuscript, signed; translation of a poem by Gerard de Nerval, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Dizain"; autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1997.
  - "Foreign Men of Letters in America"; autograph manuscript, signed, 1898 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Accompanied by biographical clipping on Lang.
  - [A History of Scotland]; autograph manuscript, signed, with corrections and revisions, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "The Ironside's Bible"; autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "A Mysterious Monk'; autograph manuscript, 1894 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 2005.
  - "A New Feature"; autograph manuscript, bound, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of Victor Tabah, 1962.
  - "Paris and Helen"; autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld, 1962.